I know what you're thinking.
أعلم ما تفكرون به الآن
You think I've lost my way,
تظنون أنني قد ضللت طريقي
and somebody's going to come on the stage in a minute
وشخص ما سيحل مكاني على المسرح خلال دقائق
and guide me gently back to my seat.
ويرشدني لمقعدي بكل لطف
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I get that all the time in Dubai.
أواجه هذه المعضلة طوال الوقت في دبي
"Here on holiday are you, dear?"
" هل تقضين عطلتك هنا، يا عزيزتي؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Come to visit the children?
" هل حضرت لزيارة الأطفال؟
How long are you staying?"
كم من الوقت ستقضينه هنا؟"
Well actually, I hope for a while longer yet.
حسناً، آمل أن أمر من هذه المرحلة
I have been living and teaching in the Gulf
لقد عشت وأقوم بالتدريس في الخليج العربي
for over 30 years.
لأكثر من 30 عاما
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And in that time, I have seen a lot of changes.
وخلال هذه الفترة شهدت الكثير من التغيير
Now that statistic
هذه الإحصائيات
is quite shocking.
مذهلة للغاية
And I want to talk to you today
وأريد أن أتحدث لكم اليوم
about language loss
عن ضياع اللغة
and the globalization of English.
وعولمة اللغة الإنجليزية
I want to tell you about my friend
أريد أن أخبركم عن صديقتي
who was teaching English to adults in Abu Dhabi.
التي كانت تُدرّس اللغة الإنجليزية للبالغين في دُبي
And one fine day,
وذات يوم
she decided to take them into the garden
قررت أن تأخذهم إلى الحديقة
to teach them some nature vocabulary.
لتعليمهم الذخيرة اللغوية المتعلقة بالطبيعة
But it was she who ended up learning
لكن أنتهى بها الحال تتعلم
all the Arabic words for the local plants,
كل الكلمات العربية للنباتات المحلية
as well as their uses --
وكذلك إستخدامات تلك النباتات
medicinal uses, cosmetics,
الإستخدامات الطبية، ومستحضرات التجميل
cooking, herbal.
الطبخ، و الأعشاب
How did those students get all that knowledge?
من أين جاء هؤلاء الطلاب بتلك المعارف؟
Of course, from their grandparents
بالطبع من أجدادهم
and even their great-grandparents.
وحتى من أسلافهم القدامى
It's not necessary to tell you how important it is
بالطبع ليس ضروريا اخباركم بأهمية
to be able to communicate
القدرة على التواصل
across generations.
عبر مختلف الأجيال
But sadly, today,
لكن اللغات اليوم
languages are dying
بكل أسف تموت
at an unprecedented rate.
بمعدل لم يسبق له مثيل
A language dies every 14 days.
لغة من اللغات تموت كل 14 يوما
Now, at the same time,
وفي نفس الوقت
English is the undisputed global language.
أصبحت اللغة الإنجليزية هي المهيمنة عالميا
Could there be a connection?
هل هناك أي علاقة بالأمر؟
Well I don't know.
أنا لا أعلم
But I do know that I've seen a lot of changes.
لكن ما أعلمه هو أنني شهدت الكثير من التغيرات
When I first came out to the Gulf, I came to Kuwait
عندما حضرت أول مرة للخليج العربي، وصلت إلى الكويت
in the days when it was still a hardship post.
في الأيام التي كانت ما تزال الوظيفة مشقة
Actually, not that long ago.
في الواقع ليس زمنا بعيدا
That is a little bit too early.
ماضي قريب نسبيا
But nevertheless,
و مع ذلك
I was recruited by the British Council,
أستلمت وظيفة من المعهد البريطاني
along with about 25 other teachers.
بجانب 25 معلمة
And we were the first non-Muslims
وقد كنا أوائل غير المسلمين
to teach in the state schools there in Kuwait.
يقومون بالتدريس في مدارس الكويت
We were brought to teach English
تم إحضارنا لتدريس اللغة الانجليزية
because the government wanted to modernize the country
لأن الحكومة أرادت تحديث البلد
and to empower the citizens through education.
وتمكين المواطنين عبر التعليم الجيد
And of course, the U.K. benefited
وبالطبع أستفادات المملكة المتحدة
from some of that lovely oil wealth.
من بعض ثروات النفط المحببة!
Okay.
حسنا
Now this is the major change that I've seen --
كان هذا تغيرا كبيرا شهدته --
how teaching English
كيف أن تعليم الإنجليزية
has morphed
قد تحوّل
from being a mutually beneficial practice
من كونه ممارسة متبادلة المنفعة
to becoming a massive international business that it is today.
ليصبح من الأعمال التجارية الضخمة عالميا اليوم
No longer just a foreign language on the school curriculum,
لم يعد مجرد منهج لغة أجنبية في المدارس اليوم
and no longer the sole domain
ولم تعد قاصرة فقط
of mother England,
على إنجلترا
it has become a bandwagon
لقد أصبحت عربة السيرك
for every English-speaking nation on earth.
لكل دولة تتحدث الإنجليزية على كوكب الارض
And why not?
ولم لا؟
After all, the best education --
فوق كل شئ، أفضل تعليم --
according to the latest World University Rankings --
وفقاً لتصنيف الجامعات عالميا --
is to be found in the universities
يوجد في جامعات
of the U.K. and the U.S.
في المملكة المتحدة والولايات المتحدة
So everybody wants to have an English education, naturally.
لذا فمن الطبيعي أن يرغب الجميع في الحصول على تعليم باللغة الإنجليزية
But if you're not a native speaker,
لكن إن لم تكن الإنجليزية لغتك الأم
you have to pass a test.
حينها ينبغي عليك إجتياز إمتحان
Now can it be right
الآن، هل يصح
to reject a student
رفض أي طالب
on linguistic ability alone?
بناء على إمتحان لغة وحسب؟
Perhaps you have a computer scientist
ربما كان عالم حاسوب
who's a genius.
وهو عبقري
Would he need the same language as a lawyer, for example?
هل هو بحاجة لنفس اللغة التي يحتاجها محامي، على سبيل المثال؟
Well, I don't think so.
حسناً، لا أعتقد أن هذا صحيح
We English teachers reject them all the time.
نحن معلمو اللغة الإنجليزية نقوم برفضهم طوال الوقت
We put a stop sign,
نحن نضع علامات الإيقاف
and we stop them in their tracks.
نحن نعطلهم من مواصلة طريقهم
They can't pursue their dream any longer,
بحيث لا يستطيعون تحقيق أحلامهم
'til they get English.
حتى يجتازوا إمتحان اللغة الإنجليزية
Now let me put it this way:
دعوني أوضح بطريقة أخرى
if I met a monolingual Dutch speaker
إذا قابلت شخص ما يتحدث الهولندية فقط
who had the cure for cancer,
ولديه علاج للسرطان
would I stop him from entering my British University?
هل سأوقفه من دخول جامعتي الإنجليزية؟
I don't think so.
لا أعتقد ذلك
But indeed, that is exactly what we do.
لكن في الواقع هذا بالضبط ما نفعله
We English teachers are the gatekeepers.
نحن معلمو اللغة الإنجليزية نعتبر حُراس المعابر
And you have to satisfy us first
ينبغي أن تجعلنا مقتنعين أولاً
that your English is good enough.
بأن لغتك الإنجليزية جيدة بما يكفي
Now it can be dangerous
الآن قد يكون خطرا
to give too much power
إعطاء الكثير من النفوذ
to a narrow segment of society.
لشريحة ضيقة من المجتمع
Maybe the barrier would be too universal.
ربما سيصبح الحاجز عالمياً
Okay.
حسنا
"But," I hear you say,
"لكن"، كأني أسمع همسكم
"what about the research?
" ماذا عن البحث العلمي؟
It's all in English."
كل شئ باللغة الإنجليزية"
So the books are in English,
فالكتب باللغة الانجليزية
the journals are done in English,
والمجلات العلمية باللغة الانجليزية
but that is a self-fulfilling prophecy.
لكن ذلك لتحقيق نبؤة ذاتية
It feeds the English requirement.
حيث تقوم باستيفاء متطلبات اللغة الإنجليزية
And so it goes on.
وهكذا تجري الأمور
I ask you, what happened to translation?
أسألكم، ماذا حدث للترجمة؟
If you think about the Islamic Golden Age,
إذا تفكرتم في العصر الإسلامي الذهبي
there was lots of translation then.
كان هناك الكثير من الترجمة حينئذ
They translated from Latin and Greek
لقد ترجموا من اللغة اللاتينية واليونانية
into Arabic, into Persian,
إلى اللغة العربية، والفارسية
and then it was translated on
ثم تُرجمت
into the Germanic languages of Europe
إلى اللغات الجيرمانية الأوربية
and the Romance languages.
واللغات الرومانية
And so light shone upon the Dark Ages of Europe.
ولذا أشاع النور عصور الظلام في أوربا
Now don't get me wrong;
الآن أرجو أن لا تفهموني خطاء
I am not against teaching English,
أنا لست ضد تعليم اللغة الإنجليزية
all you English teachers out there.
لكل معلمي اللغة الإنجليزية
I love it that we have a global language.
أنا أحب أن تكون لدينا لغة عالمية
We need one today more than ever.
نحتاجها اليوم أكثر من أي وقت مضى
But I am against using it
لكني ضد إستخدامها
as a barrier.
كنوع من الحاجز
Do we really want to end up with 600 languages
هل نريد أن ينتهي بنا الحال ب 600 لغة
and the main one being English, or Chinese?
وتصبح اللغة الرئيسية هي الإنجليزية أو الصينية؟
We need more than that. Where do we draw the line?
نحن بحاجة لأكثر من ذلك. أين نرسم الخط الفاصل؟
This system
هذا النظام
equates intelligence
يساوي بين الذكاء
with a knowledge of English,
ومعرفة اللغة الإنجليزية
which is quite arbitrary.
الذي هو تعسفي للغاية
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I want to remind you
وأرغب في تذكيركم
that the giants upon whose shoulders
بأن عمالقة المثقفين والصفوة
today's intelligentsia stand
على المشهد العالمي
did not have to have English,
لم يعرفوا اللغة الانجليزية
they didn't have to pass an English test.
ولم يتوجب عليهم إجتياز امتحان لغة انجليزية
Case in point, Einstein.
مثال حالة اينشتاين
He, by the way, was considered remedial at school
بالمناسبة، لقد تم إعتباره مريضا في المدرسة
because he was, in fact, dyslexic.
لأنه في الواقع عانى من صعوبة التعلم
But fortunately for the world,
لكن لحسن حظ العالم
he did not have to pass an English test.
لم يتوجب عليه إجتياز إمتحان لغة انجليزية
Because they didn't start until 1964
لأنهم لم يبدأوا حتى عام 1964
with TOEFL,
إمتحان اللغة "التوفل"
the American test of English.
الإمتحان الأمريكي للغة الانجليزية
Now it's exploded.
وقد تفجر الوضع الآن
There are lots and lots of tests of English.
هناك الكثير من إمتحانات اللغة الانجليزية
And millions and millions of students
وملايين الملايين من الطلاب
take these tests every year.
يجلسون للامتحان سنويا
Now you might think, you and me,
الآن ، ربما يفكر جميعنا
"Those fees aren't bad, they're okay,"
بأن تلك المنصرفات ليست مشكلة
but they are prohibitive
لكنها عائق وحاجز
to so many millions of poor people.
لملايين الناس من الفقراء
So immediately, we're rejecting them.
ولذا نقوم برفضهم على الفور
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It brings to mind a headline I saw recently:
هذا يستدعي عنوانا رئيسيا رأيته مؤخراً
"Education: The Great Divide."
" التعليم: الفارق الأعظم"
Now I get it,
الآن فهمت كل شئ
I understand why people would want to focus on English.
فهمت لماذا يركز الناس على اللغة الانجليزية
They want to give their children the best chance in life.
إنهم يرغبون في تقديم أفضل فرصة لابنائهم في الحياة
And to do that, they need a Western education.
ولفعل هذا ، يحتاجون لتعليم على نسق غربي
Because, of course, the best jobs
لأن أفضل الوظائف بالطبع
go to people out of the Western Universities,
تذهب لخريجي الجامعات الغربية
that I put on earlier.
التي عرضتها مسبقا
It's a circular thing.
إنه أمر دائري ومغلق
Okay.
حسنا
Let me tell you a story about two scientists,
دعوني أخبركم قصة عن أثنين من العلماء
two English scientists.
عالمان إنجليزيان
They were doing an experiment
كانوا يجرون تجربة
to do with genetics
ذات صلة بالجينات
and the forelimbs and the hind limbs of animals.
متعلقة بالأطراف الأمامية والخلفية للحيوانات
But they couldn't get the results they wanted.
لكنهم لم يتلقوا النتائج التي يرغبون بها
They really didn't know what to do,
ولم يعرفوا ماذا يفعلون
until along came a German scientist
حتى جائهم عالم الماني
who realized that they were using two words
الذي أدرك أنهم يستخدمون كلمتين
for forelimb and hind limb,
للأطراف الخلفية والأمامية
whereas genetics does not differentiate
بينما لا يُفرّق علم الجينات بينهما
and neither does German.
وكذلك اللغة الالمانية
So bingo,
وعليه فقد وجدها
problem solved.
وتم حل المشكلة
If you can't think a thought,
إذا لم تستطع التفكير
you are stuck.
فانت عالق
But if another language can think that thought,
لكن إن كانت لغة أخرى تستطيع التفكير
then, by cooperating,
حينها، عبر التعاون
we can achieve and learn so much more.
يمكنك إنجاز وتعلم الكثير الكثير
My daughter
جائت بنتي
came to England from Kuwait.
إلى إنجلترا من الكويت
She had studied science and mathematics in Arabic.
وقد درست العلوم والرياضيات باللغة العربية
It's an Arabic-medium school.
كانت المدرسة المتوسطة باللغة العربية
She had to translate it into English at her grammar school.
وتوجب عليها الترجمة إلى الإنجليزية في مدرستها
And she was the best in the class
وقد كانت الأولى على الفصل
at those subjects.
في تلك المواد
Which tells us
ما يكشف لنا
that when students come to us from abroad,
أنه عندما يأتينا الطلاب من الخارج
we may not be giving them enough credit
فنحن لا نُحسن تقدير وتقييم
for what they know,
ما يعرفوه بالفعل
and they know it in their own language.
وقد تعلموه بلغتهم الأم
When a language dies,
عندما تموت لغة
we don't know what we lose with that language.
لا أحد يعرف ماذا نخسر مع موت تلك اللغة
This is -- I don't know if you saw it on CNN recently --
هذا هو -- لا أدري ان كنتم قد شاهدتم مؤخراً على سي أن أن --
they gave the Heroes Award
لقد منحوا جائزة الأبطال
to a young Kenyan shepherd boy
لصبي كيني يافع يعمل راعيا
who couldn't study at night in his village,
الذي لم يستطع الدراسة في قريته
like all the village children,
مثل كل أطفال القرية
because the kerosene lamp,
لأن دخان مصباح الكيروسين،
it had smoke and it damaged his eyes.
أتلف عينيه
And anyway, there was never enough kerosene,
و ليس هناك كيروسين كافي على اي حال
because what does a dollar a day buy for you?
لأنه يكلف دولار يوميا
So he invented
لذا فقد أبتكر
a cost-free solar lamp.
مصباح بالطاقة الشمسية لا يكلف أي شئ
And now the children in his village
والآن يحصل الأطفال في مدرسة
get the same grades at school
قريته على نفس الدرجات
as the children who have electricity at home.
التي يحصل عليها من توفرت لهم الكهرباء في المنزل
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
When he received his award,
عندما أستلم جائزته
he said these lovely words:
قال هذه الكلمات الرائعة:
"The children can lead Africa from what it is today,
" بمستطاع الأطفال قيادة أفريقيا من حالها اليوم،
a dark continent,
كقارة مظلمة
to a light continent."
إلى قارة مضيئة."
A simple idea,
فكرة بسيطة،
but it could have such far-reaching consequences.
لكن يمكن أن يكون لها آثار بعيدة المدى
People who have no light,
إن المحرومين من الضوء ،
whether it's physical or metaphorical,
سواء كان مادياً أو مجازياً
cannot pass our exams,
لا يستطيعوا إجتياز الإمتحانات
and we can never know what they know.
ولن نستطيع مطلقاً معرفة ما يعرفون
Let us not keep them and ourselves
دعونا لا نحصر أنفسنا لانفسنا
in the dark.
في الظلام
Let us celebrate diversity.
دعونا نحتفي بالتنوع
Mind your language.
وأهتموا بلغتكم
Use it to spread great ideas.
إستخدموها لنشر الأفكار العظيمة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم